<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.4.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://46b.it/meta/feed.atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://46b.it/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-08-06T18:05:43+01:00</updated><id>https://46b.it/</id><title type="html">46b.it</title><entry><title type="html">Day 9: Welcome to Berlin</title><link href="https://46b.it/2017/welcome-to-berlin/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 9: Welcome to Berlin" /><published>2017-07-08T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-07-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://46b.it/2017/welcome-to-berlin</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://46b.it/2017/welcome-to-berlin/">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/hannover-to-berlin/&quot;&gt;left Hannover for Berlin&lt;/a&gt; on the second-to-last leg of &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/northwestern-europe/&quot;&gt;my rail trip across Europe&lt;/a&gt;! I can’t believe this trip is nearly over - I fly home from Prague a little before 9pm on Day 12.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;alexanderplatz-and-the-pergamon-museum&quot;&gt;Alexanderplatz and the Pergamon Museum&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The natural starting point for a day walking across the centre of Berlin seemed to be Alexanderplatz. It is a large area with monumental buildings, which leads on to Museum Island (see below) and the rest of Central Berlin. The highly-recognisable Berlin TV Tower is here, as is a Rotes Rathaus (a building I’ve seen in City Simulation games for many years with knowing where it was.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/berlin-tv-tower.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/berlin-alexanderplatz-1.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The detailing on this church seems similar to &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/amsterdam-to-hannover/&quot;&gt;the Old City Hall in Hannover&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/berlin-alexanderplatz-2.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Berlin’s Museum Island has a remarkable concentration of excellent museums. I feel that I could spend a week looking through them, easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/berlin-museum-island-cathedral.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[MUSEUM ISLAND PICTURES]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to the Pergamon Museum, which exhibits major reconstructions of large ancient structures. It’s really rather impressive but the context of the structures isn’t introduced very well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/berlin-pergamon-ishtar-wall.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/berlin-pergamon-roman-gate.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t even try to get great photos of these. They’re too large relative to the rooms to be easily photographed, and the ceiling lets in too much light to avoid glare. See Google or go to the Museum for yourself! Similar to the British Museum they have smaller artifacts as well, some of them plaster casts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/berlin-pergamon-lions.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/berlin-pergamon-figure.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hotel is around the corner from a large Muslim community centre, which was a reminder of how little I know about Islam and its cultural history. I wandered around an exhibit on Islamic Art at The Pergamon until my feet got tired, but I did find an amazing work that I believe is a vase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/berlin-pergamon-islamic-art-jug-1.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/berlin-pergamon-islamic-art-jug-2.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;brandenburg-gate-holocaust-memorial-and-checkpoint-charlie&quot;&gt;Brandenburg Gate, Holocaust Memorial and Checkpoint Charlie&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the rest of the day I visited Gendarmenmarkt, the Brandenburg Gate, the Holocaust Memorial and Checkpoint Charlie. I must confess that this is presented a little out-of-order: I skipped Gendarmenmarkt at first, only to later realise that it would have been the area to stop for lunch, and headed back there for dinner later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/berlin-gendarmenmarkt-3.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gendarmenmarkt is a large square with several magnificent large buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/berlin-gendarmenmarkt-1.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/berlin-gendarmenmarkt-2.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little further West, the area of the Brandenburg Gate reminds me of Trafalgar Square. Both are concretey urban and have impressive stonework, but I feel both somehow fail to justify their apparent tourist appeal. The area does have some things of interest - notably the Reichstag and the edge of Tiergarten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/berlin-brandenburg-gate.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/berlin-brandenburg-gate-interior.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few minutes south is The Memorial to the Murdered Jews of Europe (more commonly known as The Holocaust Memorial.) On the surface this consists of supernumerary concrete blocks set out in a disturbing, undulating grid pattern. Underneath is a Holocaust Museum that wasn’t open today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/berlin-holocaust-memorial.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Checkpoint Charlie was the main crossing point between West and East Berlin for much of the Cold War. As with much of Berlin the area has been completely redeveloped since, and all that remains of what was once there is the little hut in the middle of the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/berlin-checkpoint-charlie.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This area is quite the tourist trap and the Berlin Wall places to visit seem to be elsewhere. But there is remarkably detailed information for such a public site along a few walls on the roadside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;topography-of-terror&quot;&gt;Topography of Terror&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have the words to convey this experience, not without blubbering them out through pillows. This free collection of exhibits, on the site of the former SS headquarters, deconstructs how the Nazis built their terrible state and committed so many evils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/berlin-topography-of-terrors.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- There isn't much to say about this place. It's a detailed and haunting look at how the Nazis came to power, how they consolidated their control of the government, how they kept the populace on side, and how they pursued their terrible ends. --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think I’ve ever been somewhere where every visitor was so silent or so close to tears. If not for children, footsteps and the occasional tourguide it might be nearly silent. It mixes evidence, pictures, personal accounts and higher-level information in a way that one can’t help but find haunting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m very glad I went. The information on &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; they got the populace on side and how they &lt;em&gt;kept&lt;/em&gt; the populace on side through so many horrors is a valuable cautionary tale. But if you go then try to go with someone you can hug afterwards, or take tissues.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Yesterday I left Hannover for Berlin on the second-to-last leg of my rail trip across Europe! I can’t believe this trip is nearly over - I fly home from Prague a little before 9pm on Day 12.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 8: Hannover–Berlin</title><link href="https://46b.it/2017/hannover-to-berlin/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 8: Hannover–Berlin" /><published>2017-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://46b.it/2017/hannover-to-berlin</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://46b.it/2017/hannover-to-berlin/">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I got to Hannover, Germany. I’m here on the way to Berlin, visiting a more realistic, non-capital-city and yet thoroughly pleasant city. &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/amsterdam-to-hannover/&quot;&gt;Last night&lt;/a&gt; I wandered through much of the Old Town and down to the large Maschsee lake. Today I’m visiting &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herrenhausen_Gardens&quot;&gt;The Royal Gardens of Herrenhausen&lt;/a&gt; and hopping back on a Deutsche Bahn ICE train to Berlin.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-royal-gardens-of-herrenhausen&quot;&gt;The Royal Gardens of Herrenhausen&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gardens are divided into two areas, with half composed of short greenery and the other half of quite tall trees. The best way to show this is a satellite view, so please forgive the size of the Google Map below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;position:relative;width:100%;height:0;padding-bottom:90.05%;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d5965.481180443901!2d9.693881703646845!3d52.38798026606271!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x0%3A0x8aba2eb652d94572!2sHerrenhausen+Gardens!5e1!3m2!1sen!2sde!4v1498337882836&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:100%;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make my 12:31pm train, I got there shortly after it opened at 9am. I seemed to be the second or third visitor of the day, which was great for getting photos without people in them. Access was remarkably easy: Hannover’s main train station and main U-Bahn station are linked by a subterranean shopping mall, and from there it’s an 8 minute journey running every 7 minutes. If you visit, note that the fountains turn on from about 10am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hannover-circlefountain.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hannover-gardens-front-2.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statues guarding the front garden remind me of Weeping Angels from Doctor Who…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hannover-gardens-front.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further back there are an assortment of smaller gardens, some with roses and others with more artistic bushes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hannover-rose-garden.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hannover-rose.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hannover-little-garden.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rear garden is largely composed of trees. It has an incredibly tall waterfall, which Wikipedia claims can reach 80m high in calm weather.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hannover-fountains.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It started to rain at this point, so I tried hiding under a tree while putting on my anorak. This tree turned out be in the spray from the fountain, which was far worse than the rain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hannover-fountain-spray.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The east and west in particular have beautiful geometry from long rows of trees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hannover-tree-row.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hannover-tree-row-building.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The garden is encircled by a small canal. This ornate bridge presumably dates from the original construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hannover-boundary-bridge.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original palace was destroyed in WWII. In the early 2000s it was rebuilt (below), and now houses a Museum that I didn’t get to visit - a shame, as I’d have loved to hear more of the history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hannover-palace.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hannoverberlin&quot;&gt;Hannover–Berlin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have too much to report for the journey East to Berlin. It rained a lot, the architecture changed but not in a way I could pinpoint until Berlin, and I’m pretty tired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dull-near-hannover.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little later the rain had become quite intense, the entire window a waterfall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/rain-near-hannover.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things cleared up just in time to see a train carrying BMWs. I suppose it’s an efficient way to get them to port.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/weather-cleared-near-berlin.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/car-transporter-near-berlin.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Berlin Hauptbahnhof is somewhat more complicated (5 storeys all open plan) than I’d anticipated, and finding where tourist information was to buy a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.visitberlin.de/en/berlin-welcome-card&quot;&gt;Berlin Welcome Card&lt;/a&gt; (3 days of public transport and free/discounted attractions) took some doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/berlin-hauptbahnhof-1.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/berlin-hauptbahnhof-2.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something I meant to do throughout this trip was to document the design of everyday buildings and objects. It’s too late to make a good study of that now, but here is the design of Deutsche Bahn departure signs and a U-Bahn station in eastern Berlin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hannover-db-sign.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/berlin-ubahn-station.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have two full days to enjoy Berlin, and I’m rather fatigued. Thus I got dinner at a burger place outside the hotel (&lt;em&gt;hallo! ich möchte einen Cheeseburger und Süßkartoffelpommes, bitte&lt;/em&gt;), napped for awhile and then read up on what to do in Berlin. Bye for now!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Yesterday I got to Hannover, Germany. I’m here on the way to Berlin, visiting a more realistic, non-capital-city and yet thoroughly pleasant city. Last night I wandered through much of the Old Town and down to the large Maschsee lake. Today I’m visiting The Royal Gardens of Herrenhausen and hopping back on a Deutsche Bahn ICE train to Berlin.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 7: Amsterdam–Hannover</title><link href="https://46b.it/2017/amsterdam-to-hannover/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 7: Amsterdam–Hannover" /><published>2017-06-27T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-06-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://46b.it/2017/amsterdam-to-hannover</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://46b.it/2017/amsterdam-to-hannover/">&lt;p&gt;Previous days have been written in retrospective, as there’s been much to do and by some bizarre bad luck I managed to go away without a pen! Today however I’m able to write from trains, and between yesterday evening and today I’ve caught right up!
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s plan was simple: get up around 9am, finish packing, go to Amsterdam Centraal station and catch a Deutsche Bahn InterCity train to Hannover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why Hannover?&lt;/strong&gt; It’s about halfway into the 6-hour train from Amsterdam and Berlin, and is host to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herrenhausen_Gardens&quot;&gt;The Royal Gardens of Herrenhausen&lt;/a&gt;. It’s also in the West of Germany, in the countryside, and smaller than the capital cities which otherwise make up my trip - therefore different and interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 30°C summer weather has definitely broken. I got up to find it wet and drizzly outside. As a result I’m wearing both long-sleeves and trousers for the first time this trip! I only have one long-sleeved item so hopefully it won’t be needed for long, although I am doing laundry in Berlin tomorrow so it might be workable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/amsterdam-airbnb-street.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set off around 10:40am with a few hours to spare before the train. First stop was getting some cheap lunch from a supermarket - I’ve discovered the Albert Heijn chain has a big store near where I’m staying. For €3 they sell a very nice “Eggwrap Gerookte Zalm.” I’ve yet to translate that, but it’s sort of like an omelette wrapped around salmon, spinach and egg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Hannover I’m staying at a very nice hotel for one night, as it’s a somewhat cheaper city and therefore the cost is much less. They have a lovely-looking restaurant serving proper German food and I’d like to try it, so despite a mile of cobbles and worse I walked/carried my suitcase to Centraal to save money over getting a taxi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diverted-to-the-ruhr&quot;&gt;Diverted to the Ruhr&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once there I found an email from Deutsche Bahn warning of disruption to my journey. I then discovered my 1pm train no longer started from Amsterdam but from someplace a long way East into Germany! I wasn’t entirely sure who to talk to but ended up at the International Railteam Service Desk inside Centraal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got three answers as to what to do. The person handing out tickets to wait for help said I’d need to catch a domestic train and then a bus to join my train later in the journey (ew!) The other person near them said I could get the 3pm train instead, which wasn’t reassuring when discovering the 11am had also been disrupted. Somewhat worried about the hassle of a bus journey, I was pleasantly surprised by the helpdesk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After about 30 seconds my number got called by the helpdesk. Their immediate reaction was really rather annoyed - they evidently hadn’t been told about the disruption and had no information on what to do. They quickly rang someone up in German, presumably Deutsche Bahn, had a lively discussion and then offered me an alternative rail journey that got to Hannover at about the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That new journey Amsterdam–Duisburg–Hannover has turned out to be a lot of fun. I’ve been taking two ICE (InterCity Express) high-speed trains. The first is on the most modern ICE trains on the Amsterdam–Frankfurt route. The second is a slightly older ICE train running the Frankfurt–Berlin route, the same one through Hannover that I plan to get tomorrow afternoon to Berlin!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;amsterdamduisburg&quot;&gt;Amsterdam–Duisburg&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve noticed today how The Netherlands has a lot of sound barriers around its trainlines near settlements whereas the UK, France and Germany seem to almost never have them. It’s a real kindness to the villages and towns one passes though, particular if at night, although it does rather prevent photos!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/ice-amsterdam-frankfurt.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/ice-amsterdam-frankfurt-platform.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/ice-amsterdam-frankfurt-interior.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot;&gt; --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friend is named after Doorn, a village 5 miles in this direction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/doorn-direction.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;duisburg&quot;&gt;Duisburg&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting on ICE trains for an extra four hours has been quite comfortable and interesting. In Duisburg I talked to someone from Holland for half an hour about the local area. I’d found myself in the Ruhr, an industrial area of Germany that was singled out for crippling in the old Treaty of Versailles… anyhow. Apparently the locals describe themselves as being from “the pit” because it is such a big coal mining area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/rail-depot-near-hamm.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/house-near-hamm.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/greenhouses-near-hamm.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;duisburghannover&quot;&gt;Duisburg–Hannover&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/ice-frankfurt-berlin.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/ice-frankfurt-berlin-interior.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we speak I’m bound for Hannover, the last stop of this train before Berlin. I am slightly tempted to rejig hotels and just go to Berlin now, but I built this pitstop in to see something which wasn’t a national capital (it’s still the state capital of Lower Saxony), take a little time out and see formal gardens, a lake and a forested park. I think it’s probably a good idea!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We just stopped in a place named Hamm. 80 minutes to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hamm.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-evening-in-hannover&quot;&gt;An evening in Hannover&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like a really nice place. I dropped my bag off at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.grandhotel.de&quot;&gt;my hotel&lt;/a&gt; opposite the Hauptbahnhof and then went to explore. This first shot is of a tunnel connecting the Hauptbahnhof to the central U-Bahn station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hannover-hauptbahnhof.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spotted a huge church of (to me) unusual design in the distance and went to investigate. This is the Lutheran &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marktkirche,_Hanover&quot;&gt;Marktkirche&lt;/a&gt;. It’s really hard to convey how large this building is - far larger than it appears in photographs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hannover-architecture-1.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hannover-architecture-2.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I headed for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maschsee&quot;&gt;Maschsee&lt;/a&gt;, a vast lake to the south of the city centre. Along the way I saw the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hannover.de/en/Tourism-Culture/Places-of-Interest-City-Tours/Tourist-Highlights/The-Old-Town-Hall&quot;&gt;Old Town Hall&lt;/a&gt;, again with architectural features new to me. It was rather exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hannover-architecture-3.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Town_Hall_\(Hanover\)&quot;&gt;New Town Hall&lt;/a&gt; is vast and impressive. I was momentarily stunned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hannover-city-hall-1.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hannover-city-hall-3.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reaching the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maschsee&quot;&gt;Maschsee&lt;/a&gt; I was stunned again. It’s about 1.5 miles long, an unusual sight when right next to a landlocked city centre!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hannover-lake-1.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the near end are pitches to play &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canoe_polo&quot;&gt;Kayak polo&lt;/a&gt; and a championship match was underway!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hannover-kayak-polo.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The park of the New Town Hall is quite charming. It is almost marshy, reminiscent of University of York’s older campus that I know and love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hannover-city-hall-2.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m already very glad to have made this stop in Hannover, and there is still The Royal Gardens of Herrenhausen to come &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/hannover-to-berlin/&quot;&gt;tomorrow&lt;/a&gt;. It’s different to the capital cities I’m visiting, but far more ‘real’ while still quite modern and cosmopolitan. (Also, I got a very good deal on the hotel and the mood-lit shower plays Raindrops Keep Falling On My Head!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might wonder why I keep typing Hannover rather than the anglicised Hanover. I got in this habit because none of my reservations show up if I search for Hanover!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goodnight!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Previous days have been written in retrospective, as there’s been much to do and by some bizarre bad luck I managed to go away without a pen! Today however I’m able to write from trains, and between yesterday evening and today I’ve caught right up!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 6: Seeing more of Amsterdam</title><link href="https://46b.it/2017/seeing-more-amsterdam/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 6: Seeing more of Amsterdam" /><published>2017-06-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-06-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://46b.it/2017/seeing-more-amsterdam</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://46b.it/2017/seeing-more-amsterdam/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2017/amsterdam-tulips-pancakes/&quot;&gt;On Day 5&lt;/a&gt; I saw the Tulip Museum and Body Worlds, had pancakes, rode the tram and wandered a bit. For a few hours I’d considered staying an extra day in Amsterdam, spending most of it sunbathing in Vondelpark, and skipping Hannover. But then the 30°C weather broke and that option became relatively less appealing. Thus today is my last day here, and I wanted to round it out by learning a bit more about Amsterdam itself.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/amsterdam-palace.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amsterdam has a lot of sides to it. You could spend a partyish few days smoking weed, partying, walking through the Red Light District and (presumably not in that district) trying to get laid - but, to be honest, that only sounds fun when bringing friends along. You could spend a painful few days visiting the Anne Frank Museum and the like - but I’m mostly leaving that part of history until Berlin. You could spend a chill few days enjoying the architecture, parks, history, museums - and that’s largely what I’ve done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/amsterdam-selfie.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;amsterdam-museum&quot;&gt;Amsterdam Museum&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started out by visiting the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amsterdammuseum.nl/en&quot;&gt;Amsterdam Museum&lt;/a&gt;, with permanent exhibits on Amsterdam’s history (independence from Spain, the Golden Age, the building of the canal layout, the Nazi Occupation and 60s/70s counterculture) and temporary exhibits on fascinating bits of culture (Puck and Hans fashion designers.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d love to go back in time and try wearing the below as school uniform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/amsterdam-museum-puck-hans.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m really quite proud of how I’ve dressed so far this trip. I’ve been overweight for a long time, which naturally means a degree of body image problems. But this trip I’ve been wearing short-sleeves and shorts and it’s been great. It is no longer 35°C outside but 24°C is easily sufficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next I followed a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2017/jun/20/chips-are-down-for-belgian-frites-as-eu-acts-on-chemical&quot;&gt;tip from The Guardian&lt;/a&gt; and went to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/maps/MjGKSYg1n5k&quot;&gt;get some frites.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; They were indeed very gorgeous, especially with some sort of mayonaise that I picked at random off a list in Dutch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;canal-tour&quot;&gt;Canal Tour&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve walked a very long way every day of this trip so far. My feet hurt. Thus I needed something to do sitting down. By pure chance, Amsterdam is a city with canals whose view of the city beats that of the streets. So I went on a canal tour, for €11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/amsterdam-canaltour.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ooh, the Tulip Museum I visited &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/amsterdam-tulips-pancakes/&quot;&gt;yesterday&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/amsterdam-tulip-museum-tour.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aah, the Canal-side Rebuild I saw &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/amsterdam-tulips-pancakes/&quot;&gt;yesterday&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/amsterdam-canalside-rebuild-tour.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The building in the distance below is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hetscheepvaartmuseum.nl&quot;&gt;The National Maritime Museum&lt;/a&gt;. I didn’t get a chance to visit but I’m sure it’s amazing given Dutch history and Google reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/amsterdam-maritime-museum.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the end we went near a vast area of modern 10-storey buildings. I think the waterfront has been recently redeveloped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/amsterdam-shore-newdevelopments.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, I found myself back in Vondelpark and started to write &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/amsterdam-tulips-pancakes/&quot;&gt;yesterday’s post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/amsterdam-ducks-again.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading East towards Berlin and Prague, I think I might read the Diary of Anne Frank. I need a new book to read and while I haven’t managed to visit this trip I certainly would in future - but make sure to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.annefrank.org&quot;&gt;book online&lt;/a&gt; a week or two in advance!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a bonus picture, as I love the height difference of the black house:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/amsterdam-black-house.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">On Day 5 I saw the Tulip Museum and Body Worlds, had pancakes, rode the tram and wandered a bit. For a few hours I’d considered staying an extra day in Amsterdam, spending most of it sunbathing in Vondelpark, and skipping Hannover. But then the 30°C weather broke and that option became relatively less appealing. Thus today is my last day here, and I wanted to round it out by learning a bit more about Amsterdam itself.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 5: Amsterdam in tulips, pancakes &amp;amp; bodies</title><link href="https://46b.it/2017/amsterdam-tulips-pancakes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 5: Amsterdam in tulips, pancakes &amp; bodies" /><published>2017-06-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-06-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://46b.it/2017/amsterdam-tulips-pancakes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://46b.it/2017/amsterdam-tulips-pancakes/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Content Warning: dissected human bodies at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Body_Worlds&quot;&gt;Body Worlds&lt;/a&gt; (not icky.)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amsterdam really is full of bicycles. It’s remarkably prevalent and cyclists are remarkably confident in their right-of-way. As a cyclist myself it’s really quite stunning to watch. Sadly only watch: I tripped and grazed my hands exactly where you hold handlebars. The segregated red bicycle lanes are sometimes very clear as a pedestrian - and sometimes not.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/amsterdam-cycle-oops.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to Paris the architecture feels a lot more variable and to me a lot more charming. It’s also a lot harder to photograph: from the street you’re obstructed by the trees, and I’ve noticed that the Amsterdam Museum has a painting which deliberately omits the trees in order to focus upon the architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve wanted to visit ever since I saw the movie adaptation of A Fault In Our Stars. While a major tourist destination, it had never been on my radar until I saw how cute and exciting it was. On a related note, I really dislike how in the book they stayed in a cheap hotel sharing rooms but in the movie they had them in a fancy, expensive hotel with individual rooms…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/amsterdam-day-2-canal-1.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/amsterdam-day-2-canal-2.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tulips-and-pancakes&quot;&gt;Tulips and Pancakes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first stop was a little esoteric: the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amsterdamtulipmuseum.com/en/&quot;&gt;Tulip Museum&lt;/a&gt; in the Jordaan neighbourhood. It discusses the origins of Tulips, their introduction to Tulip Mania and how the Dutch ended up in Tulip Mania: a major price bubble in 1637 where the newly-introduced tulips were being exchanged for apparently extraordinary prices. Sadly I don’t have a great photo for this, but it’s worth a visit!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/amsterdam-tulip-museum.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About this time I’d started to feel a little bit lonely. I’m used to enjoying my own company from my teen years, but it always takes some getting used to. My sister headed home from Paris and it’s just me for the rest of the trip (another week to go!) At first I wasn’t sure how best to overcome this, so resolved to keep going about the day I’d started to plan out in my head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So next, I got pancakes! I must say, York’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://doubledutchpancakehouse.com&quot;&gt;Double Dutch Pancake House&lt;/a&gt; really stood its ground against what’s apparently a renowned (if touristy) pancake house. Mine was baked rather than fried, but otherwise was quite comparable. The below was about as much as I could eat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/amsterdam-half-pancake.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At about this time, the glorious weather thus far with 32+°C days and 20+°C nights broke in spectacular fashion. We got hit by a big rain shower, from which I had to hide a postcard as I had no bag. Then as I was hurrying back towards the central island (Centrum?) when a rather intense thunderstorm hit. As if from nowhere the people on the street changed from t-shirt-and-shorts-clad to long-sleeves-and-jeans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/amsterdam-storm.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bodies&quot;&gt;Bodies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d hoped to visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Body_Worlds&quot;&gt;Body Worlds&lt;/a&gt; while in Amsterdam and this proved an excellent place to take shelter. Lightning hit something rather close as I got my ticket, and everything shook. Thankfully the power stayed on!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the rain hit I started to feel a lot better. The hardest thing about spending lots of time by yourself (or in charge) is keeping a sense of direction, and having formed one for the rest of the day I just enjoyed the novelty of a rainstorm after so many days of Florida-like weather.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Body Worlds proved one of the most unique and fascinating exhibitions I’ve visited. It’s actually a partnership between Body Worlds and The Happiness Project, and the mix of the two works surprisingly well. Each floor is a mix of the human body (e.g., the nervous system) and the human condition (e.g., positive mindsets.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/amsterdam-bodyworlds-arteries.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/amsterdam-bodyworlds-saxophone.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top floor has the nervous system from real human bodies. Both individual ‘pieces’ and the entire thing. It’s not for the squeamish but I understand a whole lot more about my body now, and I don’t know how I would possibly have learned that without seeing quite so many bodies and parts of bodies. I’ll… stop talking before this sounds creepy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/amsterdam-bodyworlds-nervoussystem.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frightfully interesting stuff.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Content Warning: dissected human bodies at Body Worlds (not icky.) Amsterdam really is full of bicycles. It’s remarkably prevalent and cyclists are remarkably confident in their right-of-way. As a cyclist myself it’s really quite stunning to watch. Sadly only watch: I tripped and grazed my hands exactly where you hold handlebars. The segregated red bicycle lanes are sometimes very clear as a pedestrian - and sometimes not.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 4: Paris–Amsterdam</title><link href="https://46b.it/2017/paris-to-amsterdam/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 4: Paris–Amsterdam" /><published>2017-06-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-06-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://46b.it/2017/paris-to-amsterdam</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://46b.it/2017/paris-to-amsterdam/">&lt;p&gt;As I write this it is Day 6 and quite appropriately I’m sitting by 6 fountains in Amsterdam’s Vondelpark.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/vondelpark-ducks-fountains.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a quiet couple of days before reaching Berlin, so it’s time to catch up with my writing starting with Day 4’s journey from Paris to Amsterdam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First thing on Day 4, I needed to get some eyedrops. I suffer from dry eyes sometimes and they’re handy to have around. For more or less the first time I didn’t even try to ask for them in French - I thought the name would be far too esoteric to guess at. But they have a name I could have grasped at: &lt;em&gt;l’hydration les yeux&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second we caught a taxi from our hotel to Gare Du Nord, Paris’ north-bound station. The taxi was a Tesla and, while a big LCD screen is cool, I was surprised how simple its interior decor otherwise is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With about an hour to spare I found a few things to do. I got a sausage baguette and what I’d expected to be a Tartalette Citron. As it turned out I think they gave me an apple one by mistake, but it still proved a delicious farewell to Paris. I helped a few London-bound Americans who were staring at the Eurostar trains unsure how to access them - the answer being to turn right, walk 100m down the concourse to an out-of-sight escalator, and go upstairs (really rather tricky to spot.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a pretty long chat with a few Americans who were also getting lunch. Originally we started talking because the three of us seemed to be prime targets for beggars - the extent of it in Paris was honestly a surprise. For better or for worse, my experiences at the Louvre have me &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; wary. But it was interesting to talk to fellow travellers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;parisamsterdam&quot;&gt;Paris–Amsterdam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was on the 12:28 Thalys service from Paris Gare Du Nord–Amsterdam Centraal, a 3h51m journey by modern high-speed train. The overhead baggage racks could contain remarkably luggage, and then I somehow managed to sit in the seat in front of mine which was rather embarrassing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading North towards Lille and the Belgian border was quite similar to Day 1’s Eurostar journey, although I’m not sure if we were on the same train tracks. Our first major stop was Brussels-Midi (seen below), roughly 18 hours after a failed/foiled bomber at Brussels-Centrale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/brussels-station-approach.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My position on terror attacks largely focuses on the actual risk. Few terrorist attacks in the West have come close to existential damage to their people or infrastructure, and thus it is generally safe to disregard them day-to-day. But the risk to society seems somewhat greater—the media profile and political urge to take some sort of action about even the smallest attack is vast. Carrying on and keeping calm seems the immediate way to counter that individually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading on into The Netherlands I received my third new reason to thank the EU of my trip: a text from Vodafone taking credit for no roaming charges and my data/texts/minutes working throughout the EU. This only came into force last week and has made my trip far easier, cheaper and perhaps safer than it otherwise would have been!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final leg to Amsterdam was very cute. The fields with regular drainage ditches reminded me of the Norfolk Broads only on a fantastically larger scale. The motorways and a lot of the houses seemed surprisingly reminiscent of UK suburbia. Something eye-opening was the train crossing a large body of water by bridge and immediately on the other side going sharply down below the waterlevel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/netherland-drainage-intersection.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/rotterdam-platform.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;first-evening-in-amsterdam&quot;&gt;First evening in Amsterdam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amsterdam did prove to be lovely in the sun. The heatwave had temperatures around 30°C. After an fun hour wandering to my AirBNB, I was rather happy to relax in a nearby park (the Vondelpark I mention above) and do some reading. Oh, and go to a gay bar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/amsterdam-canal.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vondelpark is absolutely gorgeous in 30°C - sadly I doubt it gets that weather too often:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/vondelpark-fountain.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/amsterdam-type-of-boy-sandwich.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--
Conclusions from Paris
- The walk bit not worth doing, go towards 16th or Sacre-Coeur instead
- Paris eats and drinks late
- Use CityMapper to get around (even more useful than in London, as the transport map is quite complex)
- Paris largely because I'd have company. In practice an extremely enjoyable destination.
- I want to go back having learned more French (Duolingo.) Perhaps to the countryside or a different city, however.

&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/eurostar-st-pancras.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot;&gt;
--&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">As I write this it is Day 6 and quite appropriately I’m sitting by 6 fountains in Amsterdam’s Vondelpark.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 2: Walking Paris</title><link href="https://46b.it/2017/walking-paris/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 2: Walking Paris" /><published>2017-06-21T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-06-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://46b.it/2017/walking-paris</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://46b.it/2017/walking-paris/">&lt;p&gt;The first city in &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/northwestern-europe/&quot;&gt;my big rail trip&lt;/a&gt; has been Paris. I’ve been here before with family, but my memories were limited to a hawker at the Eiffel Tower and getting my shoelace stuck in an escalator at the Disneyland Paris train station.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--First a confession: I disliked French at school. I didn't know much of anything about France, didn't holiday there and I believe the first French person I spent serious time with was a French teacher who moved over from France and my interest in the subject did dramatically increase when under their tutoring. Perhaps the French person I know best know from startups days is Mathieu, but I haven't had time to see them.--&gt;

&lt;!--I have two full days in Paris, Amsterdam and Berlin which gives one day to explore and one day to do particular activities (perhaps, later in the trip, sleep.) Paris was a weird one in that I'm expecting to hop back by Eurostar sometime soon and had already booked Disneyland Paris for that second full day.--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t have time to include in &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/wakefield-to-paris/&quot;&gt;Day 1’s post&lt;/a&gt; our trip to the Eiffel Tower on the first night we got there, reaching the summit a little after 10pm and just as the lights came on!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/eiffel-over-buildings.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/live-street.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/sunset-over-la-defense.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we had trouble on the way to Paris we had joked that a McDonalds near the hotel was open until 2am if we were to get in that late. As it turned out we did resort to eating there, at about 1am on the way back from the Eiffel Tower! We’d assumed that it would be the only place serving food, but in hindsight I get the impression that a proper French bistro would have been able to feed us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t sleep (as is typical my first night somewhere) so got up pretty late the next day. I caught up with Sarah on the Champs de Mars (the D.C. Mall-style area in front of the Eiffel Tower), and we took in an obvious tourist route from there to the Trocadero, up past the Arc de Triomphe, down the Champs-Elysees, through the Louvre and to Notre Dame - a few hours walk. My companion wasn’t a huge fan of figuring out public transport, so walking was a little easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/sunny-street.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/trocadero-statue.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like building up mental maps of cities, but in hindsight I think the route was a mistake. Between the Trocadero and the Petit Palace end of Champs-Elysees was a fair distance and not hugely remarkable compared to the 15th we were staying in. In hindsight I’ve have caught the Metro towards Place de la Republique and spent an hour in a museum near in the Louvre, but it was still a nice walk through the architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/petit-palais.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s me on the steps of Petit Palais, in a Yorkie Swing Dance t-shirt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we reached Place de la Republique by foot we were quite exhausted. The temperature was around 35°C and the trees lining the boulevards have a gap near there (and the breeze slowed.) We stumbled on through the gardens, still having fun but really in need of a drink, and targeted a Starbucks next to the Louvre. Our eventual arrival had us both limping… a bit of fun. Jumping for the coldest thing I could imagine, I ordered a Yaourt Banana Creme: a smoothie of (frozen?) yoghurt, banana, cream and ice. It was indeed the most cooling drink I could imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/louvre-pyramids.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a long recuperation in the cool, I headed out to wander the Louvre and reach Notre Dame. I got some nice shots of the Louvre pyramids and then got severely harassed by a group of fake petitioners who evidently thought me a good target - the point where six of them started to surround me was a little scary, but I distracted them long enough to get the hell out of there! I’m curious what their relationship with the police is - if not violent they might be left alone and yet the line between the harassment and violence is very thin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that fright, I got a drink (in French, although I think I mistook how seating was supposed to work) and sat near Notre Dame. We planned to have a nice meal at a nice restaurant that evening, and I still had a few hours to use up before getting the Metro back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/metro.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d eyed a few places on Place Cambronne that had a lot of everyday French customers and looked quite nice, and we picked . It was a nice meal - Seabass and Vegetable Taglietele (spiralised and nicely cooked vegetables.) I’d been fancying some Rosé wine for days, and it is France, so I had… a little too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 3 was Disneyland Paris, but I’m not going to write that up quite yet.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The first city in my big rail trip has been Paris. I’ve been here before with family, but my memories were limited to a hawker at the Eiffel Tower and getting my shoelace stuck in an escalator at the Disneyland Paris train station.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Day 1: Wakefield–London–Paris</title><link href="https://46b.it/2017/wakefield-to-paris/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Day 1: Wakefield–London–Paris" /><published>2017-06-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-06-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://46b.it/2017/wakefield-to-paris</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://46b.it/2017/wakefield-to-paris/">&lt;p&gt;Today is the first leg of &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/northwestern-europe/&quot;&gt;my big rail trip&lt;/a&gt;. We’re taking two trains, the first from Wakefield (in Yorkshire) down to London and the second across to Paris.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first leg is fairly straightforward… in theory. A Virgin Trains East Coast service from Wakefield Westgate to London, using the Leeds Branch of the East Coast Mainline. 200 miles by rail, 2 hours, top speed of 125mph. In practice, it didn’t go so well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a farewell to our parents, the first thing we did at Wakefield Westgate was get our tickets down to London. Eurostar had provided us with a booking reservation number to collect them. We were rather surprised to get 1x Adult and 1x Child tickets, when we’re both rather older than the 16-year-old cutoff for Child tickets. After a glance at our Eurostar tickets it became clear that my Youth (12-25) ticket must have been booked with National Rail as a Child - a bug in an automated system, no doubt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wakefield Westgate ticket office couldn’t help, and my sister was booked on a specific train, so I had little choice but to buy a Super Off-Peak Single to London Kings Cross (£70 with my Railcard) and hope to receive a refund from Eurostar, given it was their mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had another 10 minutes before the train - far too little to talk to Eurostar and straighten things out - so we went to WHSmiths. Then we heard that our train to London was cancelled. Uh oh. So we waited an hour and got on the next service down - trusting that our thru-booking with Eurostar ensured no problems getting on the next leg to Paris.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/eurostar-st-pancras.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having made it to London St Pancras, Eurostar Support were fantastic in person, and we got on the 15:31 to Paris (two hours later than planned) with some vouchers to make things up to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re about 5 minutes into the Channel Tunnel now. It’s remarkable how little light is outside compared to what I recall taking the Car Transporter with my Junior School. I recall regular orange floodlights outside the window. Now there’s just regular green LEDs every 2 seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having just emerged into France, I’m struck by how huge the fields are compared to back home. Even the sparsely farmed hills of my origin are only 5 minutes walk a side - some of these I’m seeing must be as much as 20 minutes, but it does vary. I also notice the ballast is a much lighter colour, the houses a more angular and cleaner design. The pylons are different - not a million miles different, but noticably different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/eurostar-france-house.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve spent the evening going up the Eiffel Tower, but I’m out of time to finish writing or find good nighttime pictures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/tour-eiffel-looking-up.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Today is the first leg of my big rail trip. We’re taking two trains, the first from Wakefield (in Yorkshire) down to London and the second across to Paris.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Paris–Amsterdam–Hannover–Berlin–Prague</title><link href="https://46b.it/2017/northwestern-europe/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Paris–Amsterdam–Hannover–Berlin–Prague" /><published>2017-06-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-06-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://46b.it/2017/northwestern-europe</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://46b.it/2017/northwestern-europe/">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2017/new-horizons/&quot;&gt;New Horizons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; last month I talked about submitting my dissertation and planning what came next. I’m excited and a little nervous to have settled my next steps (see upcoming posts), and I’m starting with two weeks travelling Europe by train.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This trip will start to address how little of Europe I’ve visited. For many years most of my holidays have been to the USA. I’ve loved, worked with and visited Americans, and been to about 20 states. I’d like to get to know Europe better in the next couple of years, and then diversify my destinations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin with I planned a short trip to Amsterdam and Berlin. But I found some company, time and money so I’ve extended matters a lot:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;June 18th: &lt;strong&gt;Wakefield–London–Paris&lt;/strong&gt; (VTEC and Eurostar)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;June 21st: &lt;strong&gt;Paris–Amsterdam&lt;/strong&gt; (Thalys)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;June 24th: &lt;strong&gt;Amsterdam–Hannover&lt;/strong&gt; (DB IC)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;June 25th: &lt;strong&gt;Hannover–Berlin&lt;/strong&gt; (DB ICE)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;June 28th: &lt;strong&gt;Berlin–Prague&lt;/strong&gt; (DB EC)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;June 29th: &lt;strong&gt;Prague–Manchester&lt;/strong&gt; (easyjet flight)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This follows an n-shaped train route east, and I’m rather interested to see the countryside and culture change even across a relatively small part of Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along the way we’ll see Paris’s Catacombs and Disneyland, Amsterdam’s architecture, Hannover’s Herrenhäuser Gardens, Berlin’s Holocaust Memorials and Museum Island, the Elbe River Valley, Prague’s language and beauty, and lots besides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prague will be the furthest East I’ve ever been, while Mount Tamalpais near San Francisco is the most West I’ve been. Sometime soon I’d like to make the furthest North be Svalbard, and push eastward to Greece and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://intarch.ac.uk/journal/issue20/taesp_index.html&quot;&gt;Troodos Mountains in Cyprus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll hopefully be posting along the way :-)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In New Horizons last month I talked about submitting my dissertation and planning what came next. I’m excited and a little nervous to have settled my next steps (see upcoming posts), and I’m starting with two weeks travelling Europe by train.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New horizons</title><link href="https://46b.it/2017/new-horizons/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New horizons" /><published>2017-05-16T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-05-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://46b.it/2017/new-horizons</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://46b.it/2017/new-horizons/">&lt;p&gt;I handed in my dissertation two weeks ago. There’s a few things to finish up but the major things I’ve wanted to deliver this year - a cryptanalysis report, an evolutionary computing experiment, my video processing dissertation - are all done. So from my perspective I’m pretty much done and awaiting Graduation come July!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Masters year was exhausting and I’m a little burned out, so I’m hoping not to rush into anything. I’ve wanted to go travelling in Europe for a few years now but kept finding interesting internships instead. Now between University and what-comes-after I have a natural gap.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friends, culture and history put Paris, Amsterdam, Berlin and Greece on the list. I’d like to follow Archaeological data I worked with into the Troodos Mountains in Cyprus, but that would be a trip in itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“And the danger is that in this move toward new horizons and far directions, that I may lose what I have now, and not find anything except loneliness.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;—Sylvia Plath, The Unabridged Journals of Sylvia Plath&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That quote above is one a friend sent me. They’re moving back to east Asia, away from the friends they’ve made here in York and back to a different culture. I sympathise in my own way: I grew up in an isolated village and adopted York as my hometown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over these six years London, Hamburg, the San Francisco Bay Area, Cambridge, MA and a few other cities in the U.S. have gained wonderful memories as well. This shows I don’t have to worry, and yet the Plath quote remains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve chatted with a lot of people about what to do next. It needs to be a step up, and yet it’s hard to know what a step up from effective-CTO of a technically hard startup would be. Delivering in a larger organisation? “Cross-functional agile teams?” Engineering technically-harder things? Making better startup decisions the second time around?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m gonna find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--
End of the day, it just has to be rewarding and worthwhile while either paying the bills or working around them.

The UK has taken a disturbing turn in the last year, and I don't quite know what it means for my or our future.

If I want to focus on engineering I'd like to work with Distributed Systems at an organisation that does good. If I want to mix product and engineering I'd either look at Product Manager or head back into startups. If I want to

The UK has taken a disturbing turn in the last year, and I don't quite know what it means for my or our future.

head back into startups I have a choice of doing my own - Dreamforge taught me a lot about the early-stage - or finding a team and direction I like.

I've chatted with a lot of people about what to do next. Deciding on a career direction is tricky. If I want to focus on engineering I'd like to work with Microservices and Distributed Systems somewhere that does good. If I want to head back into startups I have a choice of doing my own - Dreamforge taught me a lot about the early-stage - or finding a team and direction I like.
--&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I handed in my dissertation two weeks ago. There’s a few things to finish up but the major things I’ve wanted to deliver this year - a cryptanalysis report, an evolutionary computing experiment, my video processing dissertation - are all done. So from my perspective I’m pretty much done and awaiting Graduation come July! The Masters year was exhausting and I’m a little burned out, so I’m hoping not to rush into anything. I’ve wanted to go travelling in Europe for a few years now but kept finding interesting internships instead. Now between University and what-comes-after I have a natural gap.</summary></entry></feed>